<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>neuroccm.org</title>
    <description>neuroccm.org is a resource dedicated to topics related to stroke and neurocritical care. The Blog portion of this website is dedicated to topics in stroke, neurocritical care,
 and general critical care, and the interface of these disciplines with computational neuroscience.
</description>
    <link>https://neuroccm.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://neuroccm.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 19:48:56 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 19:48:56 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>ChatGPT is asked - Write several paragraphs on why rapid presentation to hospital is important for acute stroke care</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The following is from OpenAI’s ChatGPT:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapid presentation to the hospital is important for acute stroke care because time is a critical factor in the treatment of stroke. The sooner a person receives treatment for a stroke, the better their chances of making a full recovery and avoiding long-term complications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a person experiences a stroke, the blood supply to their brain is disrupted, which can cause brain cells to die. The longer this disruption continues, the more brain tissue is damaged, and the more severe the effects of the stroke will be. Therefore, it is essential to restore blood flow to the brain as quickly as possible to minimize the damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapid presentation to the hospital allows doctors to quickly diagnose the type of stroke and determine the best course of treatment. There are several different treatments available for stroke, and the choice of treatment will depend on the type of stroke and the extent of the damage. For example, some treatments aim to restore blood flow to the brain by removing a blood clot that is blocking an artery, while others may involve medications to prevent further damage to brain tissue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to note that some treatments for stroke, such as thrombolysis, must be administered within a specific time window in order to be effective. This time window is typically within the first few hours after the onset of symptoms. Therefore, rapid presentation to the hospital is essential to ensure that the person experiencing a stroke receives the appropriate treatment as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, rapid presentation to the hospital can also help to prevent further complications from occurring. For example, a person who has experienced a stroke may be at risk of developing pneumonia, which can be life-threatening. By seeking treatment quickly, doctors can provide the person with the appropriate care and support to prevent complications from occurring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, rapid presentation to the hospital is important for acute stroke care because it allows doctors to quickly diagnose the type of stroke and provide the appropriate treatment to minimize the damage and prevent further complications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Well written, the future is bright for AI aiding in public messaging ad campaigns that require documents, advertising, and messaging for healthcare.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2022 01:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://neuroccm.org/stroke/2022/12/11/ChatGPT_Stroke.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://neuroccm.org/stroke/2022/12/11/ChatGPT_Stroke.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Stroke</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Devil is in the Details - Understanding CT Perfusion in the late EVT windows</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CT perfusion (CTP) is a powerful imaging technique that can be utilized in order to distinguish the region of infarction from the ischemic penumbra.  CT perfusion algorithms are typically proprietary, and are always dependent on hemodynamic factors.  Such factors include presence of extracranial stenosis, presence of sinus rhythm (perfusion may be affected by atrial fibrillation), systemic factors such as hypoperfusion/shock, and more technical factors such as accuracy by which contrast is given, location of selection for both the arterial and venous phase functions, and patient motion during the scan.  In an ideal study, CT perfusion is able to demonstrate the 3 typical maps that are used to make decisions, including his cerebral blood flow map [CBF], mean transit time [MTT], and the cerebral blood volume [CBV].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With thrombectomy now occurring in extended time windows (DEFUSE3 and DAWN trials), the role of CT perfusion has been markedly expanded as CT perfusion, when used appropriately, can provide insight into what brain regions can be salvageable from an ischemia and penumbra perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual the devil is in the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regards to DEFUSE3 and DAWN, the following table from a topical review by Dr. Alberts, outlines the criteria used to distinguish ischemic core and mismatch volume and the presence of a large vessel occlusion.  Similar criteria can be used an MRI imaging (perfusion imaging), however this article will focus on CTP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of note, median ischemic core volumes in both trials, are approximately 10 cc, and as evident in the table below, DEFUSE3 included ischemic core volumes up to 70 cc, with a graded approach, dependent on age and NIH stroke scale, as utilized in the DAWN trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ischemic core volume is felt to be estimated by cerebral blood flow less than 30% of normal.  This value is felt to correlate to perfusion at the cellular level being less than 20cc/100g/min of brain were critical ischemia occurs.  Recall that normal cerebral blood flow is on the order of 50-60cc/100g/min.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Campbell et al., showed that 30% of normal CBF was the optimal threshold to define the ischemic core within a Tmax &amp;gt; 6s (penumbra region), when CT perfusion was processed by standard singular value decomposition.  It should be noted that this decomposition mathematically assumes no delay in blood flow from proximal arteries to the ischemic brain tissue whereas T-max and CBF are measured. The threshold of using CBF &amp;lt; 30%, is further supported by data from the SWIFT PRIME trials, where the RAPID software was used, with this threshold of CBF strongly correlating with the final infarct volume at 27 hours inpatient to achieved reperfusion. In the study by Cereda et al., as CBF threshold of less than 38% of normal predicted DWI volumes.  However in some patients this threshold significantly overestimated the size of the DWI lesion, and therefore threshold of 30% has been used in the late window EVT trials. Cereda et al., show that a threshold of approximately 38% showed the least mean volume difference (DWI-CTP in cc), of the ischemic core.  It should be noted that if a lower percentage is selected such as 25% of normal CBF, that this underestimates the core vs. DWI (i.w. DWI-CTP becomes a larger positive number with lowering of CBF threshold under 38% -&amp;gt; towards 2%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly T-max greater than 6 seconds has been used to define the ischemic penumbra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that these computations are hemodynamic in nature, T-max also provides information with regards to collaterals.  And regions of brain with T-max greater than 10 seconds are felt to correlate with regions of poor collateral flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ratio of tissue volume with T-max greater than 10 seconds compared to T-max greater than 6 seconds is referred to as the hypoperfusion intensity ratio, and it is notable that the high rations, greater than 0.5 (i.e. 50%) correlate with poor angiographic collaterals and these patients likely have a March larger ischemic core then visualized, and the score is more likely to rapidly grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore in order to use CTP effectively, not only the fact that it is a hemodynamic calculation needs to be considered, the patient has to meet various factors as outlined, but also the details of these thresholds whereby the ischemic core and collateral status are approximated, need to be considered in order to make proper decisions with regards to the information provided by the RAPID software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Albers, Use of Imaging to Select Patients for Late Window Endovascular Therapy,Stroke. 2018;49:00-00. DOI: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.118.021011.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cereda CW, Christensen S, Campbell BC, Mishra NK, Mlynash M, Levi C, et al. A benchmarking tool to evaluate computer tomography perfu- sion infarct core predictions against a DWI standard. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2016;36:1780–1789. doi: 10.1177/0271678X15610586&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Campbell BC, Christensen S, Levi CR, Desmond PM, Donnan GA, Davis SM, et al. Cerebral blood flow is the optimal CT perfusion param- eter for assessing infarct core. Stroke. 2011;42:3435–3440. doi: 10.1161/ STROKEAHA.111.618355.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 14:11:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://neuroccm.org/stroke/2018/09/12/Details_of_CTP.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://neuroccm.org/stroke/2018/09/12/Details_of_CTP.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Stroke</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>WAKE-UP - who can get TPA outside of the 4.5 hr time-window?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proportion of patients wake up with a stroke and it is believed that in a significant fraction of these patients, the stroke occurs close to the waking hour.  Such patients, are traditionally excluded from thrombolytic treatment given that they are outside of the standard window for delivery of TPA, this being 4.5 hours (i.e. last seen normal beyond 4.5 hrs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study published in May Thomalla et al. (2018) in the New England Journal of Medicine, the authors of the WAKE-UP trial tested a hypothesis that some of these patients can be candidates for TPA, when guided by MRI imaging, specifically mismatch between DWI and FLAIR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patient that met inclusion criteria had to be, at minimum, outside of the 4.5hrs from last seen normal. The median interval was approximately 7 hrs in both the TPA and placebo groups (from last known to be well). This was a prospective, investigator-initiated multi-center, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial. Patients could undergo randomization if in the judgment of the investigator MRI showed an acute ischemic lesion on DWI imaging but not parenchymal hyperintensity (using standard) FLAIR windows. Below I have linked to the paper (imaging-based) where the scientific rational for looking beyond 4.5hrs comes from in way of DWI FLAIR mismatch (Thomalla et al. 2011).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study, 503 suitable imaging results, were randomly assigned to alteplase or placebo, and most of the patient’s in the study had mild to moderate strokes.  Primary endpoint was favorable outcome mRS at 90 days of 0 or 1. This occurred 53.3% (TPA) vs. 41.8% (Placebo group) - (adjusted odds ratio, 1.61; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.09 ­ 2.36; p = 0.02).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that this trial stopped early due to funding (approx. 2/3 of target enrollment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a trend towards increased mortality in the TPA group, but that it did not achieve statistical significance (4.1% vs. 1.2%, p=0.07). Of the 10 patients that died, 4 were due to symptomatic ICH. Rate of parenchymal hemorrhage type 2 was 4% vs 0.4% (p=0.03).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenges in implementation include the fact that obtaining MRI imaging in a timely manner is difficult and most centers. Also a large proportion of the patients in this trial were also eligible for EVT as per DAWN and DIFFUSE3 criteria  - approximately 20% of patients, which raises the possibility (unknown) of better outcome with EVT vs. late-window TPA administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken together, the findings of WAKE-UP push the boundaries of TPA administration in acute stroke care beyond the 4.5hr time window. This especially benefits those who may have had their stroke close to waking without known a “last seen normal” time - these patients may be then identified via imaging. For now, my personal opinion (comfort) is to stay within the ascribed 4.5hrs (reserving out of window TPA for special circumstances, off-label with open disclosure to the patient/SDM). It’s great however that such studies exist providing additional scientific basis for out of window TPA. Collectively some criticisms of the trial include: early termination/lack of full enrollment, large fraction of patients were EVT candidates, signal towards higher mortality, and high risk of bleeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers discovered that in patients who received TPA, they had an increased chance of a favorable outcome (mRS 0-1), at 90 days.  Indeed, this was the first positive trial for IV thrombolysis and strokes of unknown time, however there are many important aspects to the study to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, studies such as WAKE-UP emphasize the notion that when identifying brain tissue at risk/amenable to being saved, it’s less about time and more about the state of the underlying tissue.  In other words, we are on a journey to better understand the ischemic penumbra about areas of brain at risk versus areas that have completed infarction -  Tissue window (perfusion, cellular energetics, collaterals) rather than time windows based on the clinical history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time…more on collaterals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa1804355&quot;&gt;WAKE-UP NEJM Trial, Thomalla et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/896775&quot;&gt;WAKE-UP Medscape Editorial by Sue Hughes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21978972&quot;&gt;Science behind the 4.5hr time-window for DWI/FLAIR mismatch, Thomalla et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thomalla, G., Simonsen, C. Z., Boutitie, F., Andersen, G., Berthezene, Y., Cheng, B., et al. (2018). MRI-Guided Thrombolysis for Stroke with Unknown Time of Onset. The New England Journal of Medicine, 379(7), 611–622.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(editorial NEJM on WAKE-UP) Jovin, T. G. (2018). MRI-Guided Intravenous Alteplase for Stroke — Still Stuck in Time. The New England Journal of Medicine, 379(7), 682–683.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thomalla, G., Cheng, B., Ebinger, M., Lancet, Q. H. T., 2011. (n.d.). DWI-FLAIR mismatch for the identification of patients with acute ischaemic stroke within 4· 5 h of symptom onset (PRE-FLAIR): a multicentre observational study. Elsevier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 14:11:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://neuroccm.org/stroke/2018/09/01/WAKE_UP.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://neuroccm.org/stroke/2018/09/01/WAKE_UP.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Stroke</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Re-working the AHA 2018 Stroke Guidelines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2018 has been very exciting year for stroke.  There have been a number of trials that have pushed the envelope with regards to thrombectomy, and many other exciting developments such as studies extending the TPA window in addition to investigating tenecteplase as an alternate to alteplase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the world was watching, in April 2018, the American Heart Association released the stroke guidelines for the United States.  Subsequently several important portions of this guideline where removed temporarily which is an unprecedented event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.lww.com/neurotodayonline/Fulltext/2018/06210/For_Your_Patients_Stroke_Guidelines__AHA_ASA.2.aspx&quot;&gt;June addition of Neurology Today, Gina Shaw&lt;/a&gt;, interviews Dr. William Powers, who is the chair of the writing group, and discusses the challenges that the group has faced with regards to the withdrawal and the rewriting process.  The correction published in April/May, states that based on feedback from the clinical stroke community the AHA guidelines had to be revised.  In the interview with Dr. Powers, it seems that due to the summer break, the latest we can expect these guidelines to be resubmitted is in September 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of note the revisions are not going to be limited to just the sections that were withdrawn, but the entire document is going to be re-reviewed.  It seems like the writing committee has its work cut out for them, and they are going to be very careful with this revision given the high steaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself and others in the stroke community look forward to the revised document in the meantime this article in Neurology Today provides a glimpse into the complex world of guideline writing and its implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 09:44:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://neuroccm.org/stroke/2018/08/20/Stroke_Guidelines_2018AHA.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://neuroccm.org/stroke/2018/08/20/Stroke_Guidelines_2018AHA.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Stroke</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Predicting Renal Replacement Therapy in the ICU</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interesting letter published in the recent publication of the journal Critical Care by &lt;a href=&quot;/eResources/Predicting who needs RRT.pdf&quot;&gt;Nierhaus et al. Critical Care (2018) 22:201&lt;/a&gt;, highlights some important and interesting findings with regards to biomarkers and how they can predict the need for renal replacement therapy in critically ill patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is more interesting is how eloquently they referred to the fact that renal dysfunction represents likely one of the facets that forecast the progression towards multiple organ dysfunction syndrome.  This very much is what we see in the intensive care unit where renal replacement therapy if used, only addresses one aspect of the ensuing multiorgan dysfunction in patients with septic shock.  It also is an important educational point when discussing with families because renal replacement therapy only offers 1 modality of correcting the complex multiorgan dysfunction that often on its own is not able to reverse the patient’s trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this letter, they discuss a secondary analysis of the SISPCT trial, which interestingly shows that renal replacement therapy was initiated and approximately 30% of patients with severe sepsis and septic shock within the first 21 days.  Furthermore the mortality in this patient group is striking approximately at 50% on average.  Even though the article discusses the potential role for MR-proADM as a biomarker, these findings and overall percentages are sobering due to the fact that they reflect how challenging this patient population is and how renal replacement therapy not only can be helpful but also unfortunately likely heralds multi-organ dysfunction and comes with an unwelcome companion, that being a high mortality risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 09:44:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://neuroccm.org/icu/2018/08/20/RRT_in_sepsis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://neuroccm.org/icu/2018/08/20/RRT_in_sepsis.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>ICU</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Seizure captured on VR</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say it’s never too late…4 years later (and many call nights later) back to writing (hopefully!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a critical care provider, with a background in epilepsy &amp;amp; seizures, and an avid follower of technology I saw something unique on one of my favorite tech sites - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2018/1/19/16911408/vr-chat-virtual-reality-seizure&quot;&gt;theverge.com&lt;/a&gt;, written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Megan_Nicolett&quot;&gt;Megan Farokhmanesh&lt;/a&gt;. I am also a strong proponent of epilepsy awareness through my work with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.norseinstitute.org/&quot;&gt;NORSE Institute&lt;/a&gt; and felt the need to write about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a group of players using VR chat noted that one member of the virtual group was having a seizure. Kudos to the group and YouTuber Rogue Shadow VR for noticing this fairly quickly as it started occurring. It also turns out that the player was wearing more than the usual VR gear, which allowed for whole-body tracking. This, in part, is what alerted the other players that this member of the chat had collapsed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge was that none of the players were able to notify the user’s friends/family or place a 911 call - many of them were expressing concern and wanting to help. As one of the players on the VR Chat noted, these episodes can be self-limiting. However at times there can be cardiopulmonary compromise caused by either loss of the airway due to emesis/secretions in the post-ictal period (with decreased level of alertness) and also due to the cardiac consequences of a prolonged seizure (such as severe bradycardia, and others). In this case the player is likely young and without other co-morbidities, however the situation could be very different at other times. Moreover, given that this individual likely has epilepsy, there is a risk that this seizure would be prolonged or reoccur in a condition called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Status_epilepticus&quot;&gt;status epilepitcus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event raises a number of issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Greater awareness of epilepsy - please visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://epilepsy.org/&quot;&gt;epilepsy.org&lt;/a&gt; and other societies such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epilepsy.ca/&quot;&gt;Epilepsy Canada&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://epilepsyontario.org/&quot;&gt;Epilepsy Ontario&lt;/a&gt;, and also the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epilepsy.com/&quot;&gt;Epilepsy Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Greater knowledge and awareness of Photic- and pattern-induced seizures, for a scientific review see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16146439&quot;&gt;Fisher RS et al.&lt;/a&gt;, and for a more lay audience, &lt;a href=&quot;https://epilepsyontario.org/epileptic-syndromes-and-visually-induced-seizures/&quot;&gt;Epilepsy Ontario&lt;/a&gt; has some good information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As pointed out by the YouTuber Rogue Shadow VR, not only do users need to be more aware of this risk in VR for visual stimulus-induced seizures, for those with epilepsy, but so do the manufactures of VR gear. There might be a tech solution here with altered patterns, refresh rates, or other parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lastly, it would be great if platforms such as VR Chat, had a mechanism of accessing emergency services for users that may have a medical emergency while in VR. This could start by users, when they sign-up, to have on their account emergency contact information, and list of medical conditions (they are willing to disclose to the platform Only!) - such that in the event of an on-line emergency in VR, other users could ask for a moderator to join the chat and observe that is going on and then trigger the appropriate action. Of course this comes with a hornet’s nest of medical-legal implications for several of the involved parties - however, there is something to be said about safety and accountability as more activity is conducted online and a broader audience may be witness to a medical emergency.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2018 08:44:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://neuroccm.org/tech/2018/01/20/OnlineSeizure.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://neuroccm.org/tech/2018/01/20/OnlineSeizure.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Tech</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Frailty in the ICU</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[posted earlier on old neuroccm wordpress site]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that ICUs across the world are admitting a greater proportion of older patients – some of these patients have poor baseline functional status. Emerging fields such as geriatric trauma in the critically ill are a testament to this. Some would say that the concept of a frail patient is one that applies only to older (geriatric) patients – but this is not necessarily true. The reason for this is that the frail individual can be defined as “any patient with diminished physiologic and cognitive reserve”. This is a well recognized concept in Geriatrics and therefore work has been done to identify and quantify the degree of frailty in that population of patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly speaking, frail patients have a higher risk of falls, illness, unplanned hospital admissions, complications after surgery, disability and death. In the older frail patient, a major illness can be a catalyst for decline into a “new baseline” of function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, this raises the notion that we should consider frail patients, and frailty as an entity, as part of our comprehensive approach to defining co-morbid risk factors in ICU patients. At present, frailty is not well captured by common critical care admission scores…and maybe it’s time that we consider this. How should we be quantifying this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this effect a recent Canadian study by Bagshaw et al. titled “Association between frailty and short- and long-term outcomes among critically ill patients: a multicentre prospective cohort study” characterized the prevalence of frailty and used a well-established frailty score (developed originally in the outpatient setting) to look at outcomes in critically ill patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;study-highlights&quot;&gt;Study Highlights&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prevalence of frailty in ICU patients is ~ 33% (national average in Canada is ~ 7%)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multi-centre, prospective, provincial study, 6 hospitals (2 tertiary, 4 community), with hospital and post-hospital follow-up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Included all patients with age greater or equal to 50, and frailty score of &amp;gt; 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excluded moribund patients, previously enrolled in the study (those with more than once admission)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primary outcome – all cause in-hospital mortality&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondary outcomes: death, ICU or at 6 months, Health related quality @ 6, 12 months, Intensity of ICU Tx, ICU length of stay, re-admission, and serious events within the ICU (such as self extubations, re-intubations, CRBSI)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mean age 67.1, ~40% women, mean APACHE II 19.5 (SD 7), mean ICU stay (~5 days, median IQR 2-10) – it is important to note that the patients who were categorized as frail had similar ICU illness severity scores (e.g. APACHE II scores)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frail patients tended to be older, female, having experienced prior hospital admissions, and have more co-morbid conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;exciting-results&quot;&gt;Exciting results&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;higher incidence of in-hospital mortality (~32% frail vs 16% non-frail)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;longer ICU stays 7 (4-13) vs 6 (3-10) days, and also overall hospital stay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much fewer patients made it back home to live independently 22% frail vs. 44% non-frail
patients discharged with “new” dependent status ~71% frail vs. ~52% non-frail
frail patients tended to have greater hospital readmissions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;key-take-away-messages&quot;&gt;Key take-away messages&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frailty is prevalent, at least ~30% or more of patients admitted to ICUs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frailty is not just a geriatric condition
Patients with similar ICU severity of illness but worse frailty status tend to do worse and we should actively consider such factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the authors state eloquently “This suggests that an episode of critical illness in a frail patient may herald a momentous transition toward greater homeostatic instability, disability, and risk of death”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;future-directions&quot;&gt;Future directions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we need a combined score or one that considers frailty? Can this be used for prognostication? Can it help us speak with families when discussing their loved one’s trajectory?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we need a frailty score developed within the ICU setting for the ICU setting? (most current scores were developed in the out-patient setting)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://neuroccm.org/icu/2014/02/28/Frailty.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://neuroccm.org/icu/2014/02/28/Frailty.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>ICU</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Therapeutic Hypothermia – 4 weeks after protocol-changing studies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;
[posted earlier on old neuroccm wordpress site]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nov. 17th saw the on-line publication of two important therapeutic hypothermia trials in the setting of cardiac arrest. These studies were well covered by several of the top intensive care blogs. Below is an organized (selected) summary, including Scott Weingart’s (emcrit.org) recent interview with Dr. Stephen Bernard who is one of the original protocol-establishing trial’s authors. Taken together, these studies are changing practice world-wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the message is that we should continue to cool patients, likely 36 deg C is sufficient for most patients, and probably, what is more important is the avoidance of fever. Some patients may still benefit from deeper cooling. Also very interesting that the PEA/Asystole group, now included Nielsen et al.’s study, did not see benefit (some say PEA is different than asystole in terms of perfusion and may respond differently to cooling).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some commentators suggest that a brain “dose-response” curve exists – such that those with a suspected greater degree of neuronal injury may benefit from lower temperatures and/or longer cooling times – however, I think this will be difficult to show definitively while controlling for confounders. The post-arrest brain injury (and it’s extent) occurs acutely in a short amount of time and there are physiologic parameters that govern the secondary injury that ensues over the coming days – it will be challenging to assess those parameters in the acute setting. We likely need a focused physical exam (perhaps augmented by objective instruments such as pupillometry), brain imaging, and continuous EEG as parameters to study acutely that may provide us future insight on how to stratify patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;reviewcommentary&quot;&gt;Review/Commentary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMe1312700&quot;&gt;Rittenberger and Callaway’s NEJM commentary on Nielsen et al.’s article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;interesting-blogs&quot;&gt;Interesting blogs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emcrit.org – [Scott’s wee on TTM] (https://emcrit.org/podcasts/emcrit-wee-targeted-temperature-trial-changes-everything/) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://emcrit.org/podcasts/post-arrest-care-2013-i/&quot;&gt;Interview with Dr. Stephen Bernard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medicalevidence.blogspot.com.au/2013/11/chill-out-homeopathic-hypothermia-after.html&quot;&gt;Medical Evidence Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intensive Care Network &lt;a href=&quot;https://intensivecarenetwork.com/index.php/icn-activities/icn-podcasts/796-niklas-nielsen-interview-1-week-post-ttm-publication&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with Dr. Nielsen&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original research articles:*&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa1310519?query=featured_home#t=article&quot;&gt;NEJM – Nielsen et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jama.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1778673&quot;&gt;JAMA – Kim et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update [27 Dec. 2013]:* Excellent panel discussion by several leaders in ED/CCM on new perspectives on TTM. See the new [RAGE Podcast]{https://ragepodcast.com/rage-session-one/)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/index.html&quot;&gt;Back to posts…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://neuroccm.org/icu/2014/01/24/TTM.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://neuroccm.org/icu/2014/01/24/TTM.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>ICU</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
